Guide to the Toby Jensky Photograph Collection ALBA.PHOTO.055
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Toby Jensky Photographs
circa 1937-1938
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Jensky, Toby, 1911-1995
ALBA.PHOTO.055
0.25 Linear Feet (1 box)
Toby Jensky (1911-1995) was a nurse with the American Medical Bureau of the North American Committee to Aid Spanish Democracy in Spain (AMB) during the Spanish Civil War. The images in this collection were collected by Jensky in the course of her work as a nurse in Spain. The collection includes photographs of AMB medical personnel at work and leisure, including Jensky, Sara Goldblatt, Fredericka Martin, and Anne Taft. There are also images of Dr. Odio D. Perez and Jensky’s future husband, Jason Patrick (Pat) Gurney, soldiers at the front relaxing and engaged in non-combat activities, Spanish children, campesinos, civilians, medical personnel and women washing clothes.
Provenance
The Toby Jensky Photograph Collection was donated to the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives by Max Schachter in 1996. This collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University. The images in the Jensky Photograph Collection were separated from the Toby Jensky and Philip Schachter manuscript material at the time of processing.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Historical/Biographical Note
Toby Jensky was a nurse during the Spanish Civil War. She sailed for Spain on April 14, 1937, with Dr. Edward Barsky’s Fourth Medical Unit. Jensky and Barsky had been colleagues at Beth Israel Hospital in New York City. She met future husband Pat Gurney while tending his wounds. After serving in Spain, Jensky nursed at Beth Israel in New York City until her retirement. She assisted Fredericka Martin in gathering primary sources documenting the history of the American Medical Bureau of the North American Committee to Aid Spanish Democracy in Spain (AMB). She died on April 25, 1995 in Sandisfield, Massachusetts. For further biographical information on Toby Jensky see the Guide to the Toby Jensky and Philip Schachter Papers, ALBA #55
Scope and Content Note
Series I: Photographs. The Jensky Photo Collection consists predominantly of photographs related to the AMB’s work in Spain during the Civil War. The collection contains photographs of AMB nurses including Jensky, Sara Goldblatt, Fredericka Martin, Anne Taft, and images of Dr. Odio D. Perez. One photograph depicts a group of AMB nurses in front of an ambulance donated by the MacKenzie-Papineau Battalion and the Communist Party of Canada. The collection also contains images of soldiers at the front relaxing and engaged in non-combat activities, Spanish children, campesinos, civilians, medical personnel and women washing clothes. All of the photographs except six were taken in Spain during the Civil War. Three photographs of Jensky were taken onboard the S.S. Normandie on its way to Spain. The two photographs of Jason Patrick Gurney were taken outside of Spain. One is a passport photograph and one is an image of Gurney with an unidentified man. There is also one image of AMB volunteers on a ship.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically by topic.
The photographic prints are identified by four numbers separated by colons. The first number refers to the collection number, the second to the box number, the third to the folder number, and the fourth to the individual print. For example, the first print in this collection is labeled 55:1:1:1.
The files are grouped into 1 series:
Missing Title
Series I, Photographs
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Toby Jensky and Philip Schachter Manuscript Collection, ALBA 55.
Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |x Children.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Personal narratives.; Black-and-white photographs.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Women.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Pictorial works.; Taft, Anne, 1912-1990; Gurney, Jason.; Jensky, Toby, 1911-1995; Goldblatt, Sana.; North American Committee to Aid Spanish Democracy; Medical Bureau to Aid Spanish Democracy; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Brigada Internacional, XV; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Martin, Fredericka I.; Perez, Odio D.
- Series I: Photographs
  - American Medical Bureau: Nurses, circa 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - At the Front: Non-Combat, circa 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Barsky, Edward K., circa 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Behind the Lines: Daily Life of the Soldiers, circa 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Behind the Lines: Rest and Relaxation, circa 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Gurney, Jason Patrick, undated, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Injured Soldiers, circa 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Jensky, Toby: At the Front, Non-Combat (includes Sara Goldblatt and Anne Taft), undated, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Jensky, Toby: With other Medical Personnel (includes Sara Goldblatt, Anne Taft, and Dr. Odio E. Perez), circa 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Jensky, Toby: Rest and Relaxation (includes Sara Goldblatt and Jason Patrick Gurney), circa 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Jensky, Toby: Shipboard ( S.S. Normandie), circa 1937 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Martin, Fredericka, circa 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Spanish Children, circa 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Spanish Civilians, circa 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Spanish Campesinos, circa 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Spanish Countryside, circa 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Spanish Medical Personnel, circa 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Spanish Workers: Laundrywomen, circa 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Volunteers on Ship (negative), circa 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 19)